Guide to the J. M. Barrie Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Other Papers, 1876–1977; Series III; 25.2; 22 boxes + 1 art
  - Personal Papers
    - Academic books and writings
      - "The World in Chains…", 1880 December 6 (Box 56, Folder 1155)
        Autograph manuscript; in school notebook with marbled paper wrappers.
      - "Immaterialism", 1881 March 18 (Box 56, Folder 1156)
        Autograph manuscript prepared for "Logic and Metaphysics" course at University of Edinburgh; in school notebook with marbled paper wrappers.
      - "English Literature Home Work No. 1", 1881 (Box 56, Folder 1157)
        Autograph manuscript notes for David Mather Masson's class at the University of Edinburgh. First leaf signed and dated: "1881 J.M.B."
      - "Historical Course I. English Literature", 1881 (Box 57, Folder 1158)
        Autograph manuscript notes for David Mather Masson's class at the University of Edinburgh. First leaf signed and dated: "Session 1881-2 J. M. Barrie." Leaf 19 written on both sides. Notebook bound in green paper.
      - "The Reliability of Consciousness", undated (Box 57, Folder 1159)
        Autograph manuscript, signed, of an essay written for a course in Moral Philosophy at the University of Edinburgh. It contains corrections and an initialed note by Professor Henry Calderwood: "A very good Essay; some points exceedingly well stated; the close somewhat incomplete. H.C."
    - Freeman honors
      - Jedburgh burgess certificate, 1928 (Box 57, Folder 1160)
        Engraved certificate printed on vellum and signed by Jedburgh town clerk T. Colledge Halliburton, with red paper seal, issued to Barrie when he became a freeman of the village on October 15, 1928.
      - Edinburgh ceremony newspaper clipping, 1929 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 1168)
      - Kirriemuir ceremony newspaper clipping, 1930 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 1169)
    - "Gaps", [1918] (Box 57, Folder 1161)
      Autograph notes of a hypothetical list of literary and historical items to be sold at the 4th Red Cross Sale at Christies', held April 1918, with initialed note: "I read these to the committee and found that the lady secretary had taken the items seriously and made a full note of them." Accompanied by a printed circular letter. Barrie was chair of the "Books, Manuscripts, and Autograph Letters Section" of the sale.
    - "George's Death", undated (Box 57, Folder 1162)
      Autograph notes of the death and burial of George Llewelyn Davies in France in 1915.
    - Indenture, 1937 (Box 57, Folder 1163)
      Autograph manuscript draft of an indenture made between Barrie and Princess Margaret; the first leaf is missing. Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from Queen Elizabeth (consort of George VI, King of Great Britain) regarding the signed indenture.
    - Indenture, 1937 June 10 (Box 54, Folder 1121)
      Manuscript document on parchment in an unidentified hand naming Her Royal Highness, the Princess Margaret as collaborator with Barrie on The Boy David. Signed by Barrie and the Princess, and witnessed by Queen Elizabeth and Sir Reginald Poole.
    - Medical notes concerning Nicholas Llewelyn Davies, 1923 February (Box 57, Folder 1164)
      Autograph notes concerning an appendectomy performed on Nicholas Llewelyn Davies.
    - Order of Merit certificate of membership, 1922 January 2 (Box 57, Folder 1165)
      Signed by George V and Colonel Henry C. Legge.
      Gift of Charles A. Stonehill, 1949.
    - Will, 1937 (Box 57, Folder 1166)
      Certified copy of will written June 14, 1937. Extracted from the Principal Registry of the Probate Divorce and Admiralty Division of the High Court of Justice, and signed by the Registrar.
    - Newspaper clippings, miscellaneous, 1930–1934 (Box 54, Folder 1122)
  - Graphic Material
    - Portraits of J. M. Barrie
      Other portraits of Barrie appear in the collection, including in some bound volumes; a group portrait with his Allahakbarrie Cricket Club can be found in the correspondence file of Edward Tennyson Reed (Series I, Box 13).
      - Artwork
        - Nicolas Bentley, caricature, undated (Box 59, Folder 1171)
          Ink on paper, signed lower right: "Nicolas Bentley" and titled at lower left: "Sir James Barrie"; stamped on verso: "Sunday Telegraph" with a note in pencil: "S/T Books."
        - Gilbert Keith Chesterton, sketchbook, 1892 (Box 59, Folder 1172)
          On one page, "Barrie" appears in a list of names surrounded by six pencil caricature sketches. Bound in quarter black sheep and black paper over boards with: "G. K. Chesterton / (aged about 18 ) / 1892 / Drawings. / Three lines of an unpublished / poem and early signature." written in an unidentified hand on a label on the front cover.
        - Thomas Downey
          - Caricature, undated (Box 59, Folder 1173)
            Ink on card, signed center bottom: "J. M. Barrie F. O. S. Thos. Downey."
          - Caricature, undated (Box 60, Folder 1183)
            Gouache on board mounted on board. Signed lower left corner; "J. M. Barrie" and lower right: "Thos. Downey."
        - Harry Furniss, sketch portrait, undated (Box 59, Folder 1174)
          Ink on paper; inscribed below image: "The first time I saw Barrie / (my thumb-nail sketch."
        - Thomas Lennox Gilmour, sketch portrait, undated (Box 59, Folder 1175)
          Two cabinet card photographs of Gilmour's sketch portrait, published as the frontispiece in The Greenwood Hat. Both are inscribed and signed at bottom: "When a mans single J M Barrie."
        - "L. B. J.," portrait, circa 1900 (Box 59, Folder 1176)
          Watercolor and ink on board; signed lower right in monogram "LJB," and inscribed underneath by Barrie.
        - Peter Scott, portrait, 1934 (Box 61 (Art))
          Oil on canvas, signed lower left: "Peter Scott 1934."
        - Joseph William Simpson, caricature, 1906 (Box 59, Folder 1177)
          Ink on paper, signed upper right: "Simpson." Published in Lions, Caricatured by Joseph Simpson (New York and San Francisco: Morgan Shepard Co., 1906).
        - "W. F. T.," portrait, circa 1895 (Box 59, Folder 1178)
          Ink on Bristol board, signed lower left in monogram: "WFT." Barrie sits in an open window smoking a pipe and drawing a portrait of a gentleman. At lower right is a telegram addressed to "Walker London." A clipped signature of Barrie is affixed to the upper right corner.
      - Photographs
        - Barrie and his mother Margaret, undated (Box 59, Folder 1179)
        - Barrie and Michael Llewelyn Davies, 1911 (Box 59, Folder 1180)
          Portrait by Lizzie Caswall Smith, signed by Barrie. Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from Nicholas Llewelyn Davies (November 9, 1950) suggesting a date for the photograph.
        - Studio portraits, 1882–1910 (Box 59, Folder 1181)
          Includes portraits by Frederick Hollyer, G. C. Beresford, and other photographers. Verso of one image inscribed: "J. M. Barrie Novelist recently divorced—expected to marry Pauline Chase." Also present is one snapshot photo and an undated photo postcard of three unidentified people.
        - Studio portrait, undated (Box 60, Folder 1184)
      - Printed portraits, undated (Box 59, Folder 1182)
        Includes a postcard, portraits cut from serials (including one by Alvin Langdon Coburn from The Century ), and a sketch portrait by William Rothenstein. One of the other 1909 photogravure portraits by Coburn is bound in with the manuscript of "Who Picked Sylvia's Pocket?" (in Box 55).
    - Portraits of colleagues
      - Charles A. Buchel, portrait of Hilda Trevelyan, undated (Box 60, Folder 1185)
        Charcoal on illustration board, signed at lower left: "Charles Buchel."
        Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Fletcher, 1960.
      - Photographs of Irene Vanbrugh, 1888–1914 (Box 62 (Oversize))
        Album with 177 photographs by commercial photographers showing Vanbrugh in roles created by Barrie, Henry James, Somerset Maugham, Arthur Wing Pinero, Oscar Wilde, and other playwrights, as well as studio portraits. All photographs are captioned and dated.
      - Unidentified artist, sketches of George, Peter, Michael, and Nicholas Llewelyn Davies, 1912 August (Box 60, Folder 1186)
        Eight graphite sketches of the boys on a fishing holiday at Scourie Lodge, Scourie, Sutherland, Scotland; scenes include the River Laxford. The sketches are unsigned and are mounted on one sheet of paper.
    - Productions and publications
      - The Admirable Crichton
        - Cora L. MacGeachy portrait of William Gillette, 1904 December (Box 60, Folder 1187)
          Watercolor and crayon on illustration board; signed lower left: "Cora MacGeachy / 1904." Inscribed on verso: "Cora McGeachy / Dec. 1904 / Xmas / W. G. in 'The Admirable Crighton [sic]' / (On the Island).'" From the 1903 production.
        - Charles S. Ricketts, design for Lillah McCarthy's costume, 1916 (Box 60, Folder 1188)
          Graphite and watercolor on illustration board; design for Lillah McCarthy's costume as Lady Mary in the 1916 Star and Garter production. Paper label on backing: "City of Manchester Art Gallery 6029. From Colnaghi."
        - Hugh Thomson illustrations, 1914 (Box 63 (Oversize), Folder 1192-1196)
          Twenty-four ink and watercolor drawings, some signed. Many are published in The Admirable Crichton (London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1914).
        - Photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 64, Folder 1197)
        - Photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 60, Folder 1189)
      - Alice-Sit-By-The-Fire: photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 64, Folder 1198)
      - Dear Brutus
        - David Broadfoot Carter drawing, undated (Box 65 (Oversize), Folder 1214)
          Drawing, gouache on illustration board, signed lower right: "D Broadfoot Carter."
        - Photograph of actors, undated (Box 64, Folder 1199)
          Including William Gillette and Helen Hayes.
      - Little Mary: photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 64, Folder 1200)
      - The Little Minister
        - T. E. Donnison, title page design, undated (Box 64, Folder 1201)
          Ink on card, signed lower right: "T. E. Donnison."
        - Phil May, illustration, 1898 (Box 64, Folder 1202)
          Ink on paper, signed lower right: "Phil May 98."
        - Edward Tennyson Reed, "The Return of the 'Little Minister.' - A Sequel", 1901 (Box 65 (Oversize), Folder 1215)
          Caricature of Lord Rosebery, ink on Bristol board, signed lower right: "E. T. Reed." Reproduced in Punch, November 20, 1901. The caricature is based on Barrie's character Gavin Dishart in The Little Minister.
        - Unidentified artist, "Sketches from J. M. Barrie's Dramatization of the Little Minister as presented by Miss Maude Adams", circa 1898 (Box 66, Folder 1221)
          Manuscript book with text in black and red ink, and illustrations drawn in black ink or clipped from publications and pasted in. The work is unsigned and undated.
          Custodial History
          Formerly in the collection of the Charlotte Cushman Club, Philadelphia.
        - Photographs of theater and film actors and scenes, 1910–1934 (Box 64, Folder 1203)
          Includes photographs from the 1934 RKO Pictures film starring Katharine Hepburn.
      - Mary Rose: photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 64, Folder 1204)
      - Peter Pan
        - Photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 64, Folder 1205-1206)
        - Photograph of Maude Adams, undated (Box 60, Folder 1190)
        - Frank Gillett illustrations, 1905 (Box 60, Folder 1191)
          Nine illustrations on one sheet, ink on Bristol board, signed at lower right: "Frank Gillett." From the 1905 production starring Cecilia Loftus as Peter Pan and Hilda Trevelyan as Wendy.
        - William Nicholson
          Nine costume design drawing in ink, gouache, and watercolor on paper and illustration board.
          - Costume designs, circa 1904 (Box 67 (Oversize), Folder 1222-1226)
            Drawings for Peter Pan, Tiger Lily, Cecce Petrucci, Starkey, and William Cookson.
          - Costume designs, circa 1904 (Box 68 (Oversize), Folder 1227-1230)
            Drawings for Indian Brave, Indian Squaw, and two drawings for Eskimos.
          - Nine wood and pulp boards formerly backing costume drawings, undated (Box 69 (Oversize))
        - Arthur Rackham
          - Illustrations, 1905 (Box 65 (Oversize), Folder 1216-1220)
            Five pen and ink drawings, some signed and dated. Published in Barrie's Peter Pan in Kensington Gardens (London: Hodder & Stoughton, 1906).
          - Printing plates, 1912 (Box 64, Folder 1207-1209)
            Three copper-faced steel plates with illustrations for a 1912 edition of Peter Pan in Kensington Gardens: 11) "Kensington Gardens are full of dogs"; 19) "It amused the birds to see him lifting the crust"; and 31) "He would make the most beautiful music."
        - Walt Disney Productions animation cel, 1952 (Box 70 (Oversize))
          Gouache on illustration board with celluloid overlay, titled and signed on the window mat. At lower left: "Walt Disney's 'Peter Pan'" and at lower right: "original WDP [in monogram]; inscribed below monogram: "To Sir Evelyn Baring / All Best Wishes / Walt Disney."
      - Quality Street
        - Hugh Thomson illustrations, 1913 (Box 71, Folder 1231-1234)
          Fourteen drawings in ink and watercolor on paper, which were published in Barrie's novel Quality Street (London: Hodder & Stoughton, 1913). Some were mounted on cardboard or illustrations board, and two are signed. Included are designs for the title page and titles for acts 2-4.
        - Photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 64, Folder 1210)
      - Sentimental Tommy: William Hatherell illustrations, 1896 (Box 64, Folder 1211)
        Six drawings, gouache on illustration board, signed and dated. They are six of eleven drawings made for the story's serialization in Scribner's Magazine 19-20 (January-November 1896) and were run again when the novel was published in book form (New York: Scribner's, 1896).
      - Tommy and Grizel: Bernard Partridge illustrations, 1899–1900 (Box 72 (Oversize), Folder 1235-1241)
        Seven drawings, ink and watercolor on illustration board, lower right: "Bernard Partridge." They are seven of eleven drawings made for the story's serialization in Scribner's Magazine 27-28 (January-October 1900) and were published again when the novel was published in book form (New York: Scribner's, 1900).
      - What Every Woman Knows: photographs of theater actors and scenes, undated (Box 64, Folder 1212)
      - Miscellaneous photographs of theater actors, undated (Box 64, Folder 1213)
        Two photographic postcards: Dorothea Baird and Henry Irving in The Wedding Guest, and "E. S. Willard as The Professor."
  - Realia
    - Portrait bust of J. M. Barrie, 1922 (Box 73)
      Copper-plated cast plaster; 25 cm in height. On front of base: "Barrie"; on verso of base: "Art Products Ld. - Copyright -1922."
    - Inkwell, undated (Box 74)
      Pewter inkwell with ceramic insert, maker unknown. Accompanied by autograph note from T. J. Read: "This pewter inkwell belonged to the Late Sir James Barrie of 3 Robert Street Adelphi WC2. He gave it to my father who passed it on to me. My father Mr. W. J. Read was Housekeeper at 3 Robert St for approximately 40 years."
    - Kensington Gardens gate key, 1903 (Box 74)
      Steel key with "E R / Kensington Gardens" and "J.M.B." engraved on either side of the bow. The key was secured for Barrie's use by Lord Esher, Secretary to His Majesty's Office of Works. Accompanied by a typed letter, signed and dated October 30, 1903, from A. I. Durrant, H. M. Office of Works. See also the letter from Lord Esher in Series I, Box 6.
    - Chateau de Bettancourt "medal", circa 1918 (Box 74)
      Copper and enamel pendant made by the Artificers' Guild Ltd., London. It was presented by Barrie to his friend Elizabeth Lucas who was for fifteen months director of an orphanage she founded in a château at Bettancourt, near Rheims, France; Barrie had partially funded her work. The inscriptions "JMB / Vive la France / EL" and "Chateau de / Bettancourt / 1915-16" are worked in copper wire set in blue enamel on opposite sides of the pendant. Accompanied by two notes of explanation and five photographs of the children and their nurses.
  - Ephemera
    - Adams, Maude, stock certificates, 1899–1910 (Box 75, Folder 1242)
      Documenting shares purchased by Adams from mining companies in Colorado, Utah, and Wyoming; one is from "The Little Minister Mining Company."
    - Aldine Club menus from Barrie-Nicoll dinner, 1896 November 5 (Box 75, Folder 1243)
      Three printed menus for dinner in honor of James M. Barrie and W. Robertson Nicoll; each has portrait of Barrie printed on tissue, and each menu was signed by many of the guests.
    - Bergner, Elisabeth, newspaper clippings, 1936 (Box 54, Folder 1123)
    - "Censorship of Plays", [1907] (Box 75, Folder 1244)
      Two typescripts of a petition protesting government censorship of dramatic productions. One is signed by Thomas Hardy and accompanied by an envelope addressed to Barrie with note: "Certainly. Though I suppose I can hardly call myself a dramatic author, can I? T.H." The other typescript is signed by Frederic Harrison.
    - Clipping: announcement of Barrie's marriage to Mary Ansell, 1894 July 10 (Box 75, Folder 1245)
    - Peter Pan
      - Autographs of actors associated with the play, undated (Box 75, Folder 1246)
        Notes signed by Nina Boucicault and George Shelton.
      - Feilden, Norman L., autograph album, 1906–1918 (Box 75, Folder 1247)
        Contains autographs, sketches, and watercolors. Leaf [2] has Barrie's autograph excerpt from Peter Pan, signed and dated 1907.
      - Playgoers' Club "Peter Pan Dinner" program, 1912 (Box 75, Folder 1248)
        Clement Shorter's copy of the program for the dinner held at the Hotel Cecil, December 22, 1912, with signatures of J. M. Barrie, Nina Boucicault, Pauline Chase, Gerald du Maurier, and Hilda Trevelyan. Includes the poem "To J.M.B." from "J.M.B.," signed by J. M. Bulloch. Accompanied by two typed letters to Shorter from du Maurier with rubber-stamped signatures, and an autograph letter, signed, from Marie Belloc-Lowndes to Shorter.
      - Programs for productions in London, Paris, and Oxford, 1904–1974 (Box 75, Folder 1249)
        Productions star Nina Boucicault, Pauline Chase, and Anita Harris as Peter Pan.
      - Sheet music for "Peter Pan" song inspired by the play, 1922 (Box 54, Folder 1124)
    - The Play Actors, London, circa 1922 (Box 75, Folder 1250)
      Printed prospectus announcing the Play Actors' Season of 1922-1923, signed by Gerald du Maurier and autographed by Barrie and other members of the group.
    - Manuscript storage containers made for Cynthia Asquith, undated (Box 76-77)
      Cloth covered containers made to hold Barrie manuscripts; each has an autograph title clipped from a Barrie manuscript title page.
    - Tempest, Marie
      - Newspaper clippings related to her jubilee celebration, 1935 (Box 75, Folder 1251)
      - Newspaper clippings related to her jubilee celebration, 1935 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 1170)
  - Writings by Others
    - Birkin, Andrew, "The Lost Boys", 1977 (Box 78, Folder 1252-1254)
      Script for a BBC production.
    - Davies, Michael Llewelyn, "Eilean Chona", 1922 (Box 78, Folder 1255)
      Two sonnets published posthumously in the Eton College Chronicle, no. 1815 (June 15, 1922), with a manuscript correction by Barrie. Accompanied by an envelope addressed by Barrie to Charles Scribner.
    - Donnelly, Arthur J., "The Shilling Briar", 1922 (Box 78, Folder 1256)
      Typescript, signed, of a book about pipe smoking. "This Edition is Limited To Four signed and numbered Copies, of which this is Number Three." Copies one and two were presented to Alfred Dunhill and A. A. Milne, and copy four kept by the author. Copy three was presented to "Sir James M. Barrie in Homage to 'My Lady Nicotine'."
    - Dunbar, Janet, "J. M. Barrie: The Man Behind the Image", circa 1969 (Box 78, Folder 1257)
      Fragment of an autograph manuscript; published by Collins in 1970.
      Gift of Janet Dunbar, 1974.
    - Moulton, Louise Chandler, "James Matthew Barrie: His Place in Literature", 1892 (Box 78, Folder 1258)
      Autograph manuscript, signed. Published in Lippincott's Monthly Magazine 49 (May 1892): 633-35.
    - Muirhead, James F. (James Fullarton), "The Queen's Dolls' House", 1924 (Box 78, Folder 1259)
      Typescript, with manuscript revisions in an unidentified hand, of a description of Queen Mary's Dolls' House built in 1924. Published in The Youth's Companion 13, no. 35 (August 28, 1924). James M. Barrie's "Autobiography" is one of the volumes listed in the miniature library.
    - Nakajima, Sueje, "The Position of Sir James Barrie as a Playwright for a Commercial Theatre", [1956] (Box 78, Folder 1260)
      Typescript, corrected. Translated into his "Shogyo gekijo sakka to shite no zemusu Barii no ichi," published in (Rissho University) Bungakuba ronso 6 (September 1956).
    - Norman, Mrs. George, "The Young Visiters", [1920] (Box 78, Folder 1261)
      Typescript of a three-act dramatization by Mrs. George Norman and Margaret Mackenzie of the novel by Daisy Ashford. Produced in London, February 24, 1920, at the Court Theatre. In tan paper wrappers.
    - Pielmeier, John, "Courage", undated (Box 78, Folder 1262)
      Printed version of typescript of "an address to the students of St. Andrew's Academy adapted from the writings of J. M. Barrie."
    - Westley, J. O., "James Matthew Barrie", 1891 (Box 78, Folder 1263)
      Autograph manuscript notebook about Barrie, with excerpts copied from his works, five clipped images of Barrie and Auld Licht churches, and a short note from Barrie to Westley.
    - Unidentified author, "The Young Visiters", undated (Box 78, Folder 1264)
      Typescript of a dramatization by an unknown author of the novel by Daisy Ashford. Although Barrie is known to have made a dramatization of The Young Visiters, it is unlikely that this is his version. In gray paper wrappers.